<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="rfc7991bis.rnc"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>
<rfc
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  category="std"
  docName="draft-xxx-idr-bgp-oad-latest"
  ipr="trust200902"
  obsoletes=""
  updates=""
  submissionType="IETF"
  xml:lang="en"
  version="3">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="One Administrative Domain">One Administrative Domain using BGP</title>

    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-xxx-idr-bgp-oad-00"/>

    <author fullname="fullname [REPLACE]" initials="Initials [REPLACE]" role="editor" surname="Surname [REPLACE]">
      <!-- [CHECK]
             * initials should not include an initial for the surname
             * role="editor" is optional -->
    <!-- Can have more than one author -->

    <!-- all of the following elements are optional -->
      <organization>Organization [REPLACE/DELETE]</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->
          <street>Street [REPLACE/DELETE]</street>
          <city>City [REPLACE/DELETE]</city>
          <region>Region [REPLACE/DELETE]</region>
          <code>Postal code [REPLACE/DELETE]</code>
          <country>Country [REPLACE/DELETE]</country>
          <!-- Uses two letter country code -->
        </postal>
        <phone>Phone [REPLACE/DELETE]</phone>
        <email>Email [REPLACE/DELETE]</email>
        <!-- Can have more than one <email> element -->
        <uri>URI [REPLACE/DELETE]</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2022"/>

    <area>Routing</area>
    <workgroup>Inter-Domain Routing</workgroup>

    <keyword>BGP OAD Confederation</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        RFC 5065 describes an extension to BGP that may be used to create a
        confederation of autonomous systems that is represented as a single
        autonomous system to BGP peers external to the confederation, thereby
        removing the "full mesh" requirement.  This documents relaxes the
        single-autonomous-system representation to provide more flexibility for
        networks that span more than one autonomous system.  These networks are
        known as One Administrative Domain (OAD).
      </t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>
    <section>
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>
        This documents relaxes the single-autonomous-system representation
        defined in <xref target="RFC5065"/> to provide more flexibility for
        networks that span more than one autonomous system.  These networks are
        known as One Administrative Domain (OAD).
      </t>

      <section>
        <name>Requirements Language</name>
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
          "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT
          RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
          interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
          <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in
          all capitals, as shown here.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>Discussion</name>
      <t>[Justification TBD. Point at use cases, etc.]</t>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>Operation</name>
      <t>
        The use of the AS Confederation Identifier <xref target="RFC5065"/> is
        OPTIONAL.  If it is configured, it MAY be used in transactions with
        peers that are not members of the OAD.
      </t>
      <t>
        A member of the OAD MUST use its Member-AS Number in all transactions
        with peers that are members of the same OAD.
      </t>
      <t>
        A BGP speaker receiving an AS_PATH attribute containing an autonomous
        system matching its own AS Confederation Identifier MAY treat the path
        in the same fashion as if it had received a path containing its own AS
        number.
      </t>
      <t>
        [More about Loop Detection]
      </t>
      <t>
        AS_CONFED_SEQUENCE and AS_CONFED_SET <xref target="RFC5065"/> MUST NOT
        be used by members of an OAD.  The use of BGP confederations
        <xref target="RFC5065"/> inside a member of an OAD is outside the scope
        of this document.
      </t>


      <section>
        <name>AS_PATH Modification Rules</name>
        <t>
          If the AS Confederation Identifier is not used for transactions with
          peers that are not members of the local OAD, the procedures specified
          in Section 5.1.2 of <xref target="RFC4271"/> do not change.
        </t>
        <t>
          [Add text about OPTIONAL modifications to the AS-PATH.]
        </t>
        </section>

        <section>
          <name>One Routing Domain</name>
          <t>
            It is reasonable for Member Autonomous Systems of an OAD to share a
            common administration and Interior Gateway Protocol (IGP)
            information for the entire domain.  It is also reasonable for each
            Member-AS to run an independent IGP.  In the latter case, the
            NEXT_HOP may need to be set using policy (i.e., by default it is unchanged).
          </t>
          <t>
            In both cases, all iBGP attributes are propagated to other peers in
            the same OAD.
          </t>
      </section>

      <section>
        <name>MED and LOCAL_PREF Handling</name>
        <t>
          It SHALL be legal for a BGP speaker to advertise an unchanged
          NEXT_HOP and MULTI_EXIT_DISC (MED) attribute to peers in a
          neighboring Member-AS of the local OAD.
        </t>
        <t>
          An implementation MAY compare MEDs from different Member Autonomous
          Systems of the same OAD.
        </t>
        <t>
          In addition, the restriction against sending the LOCAL_PREF attribute
          to peers in a neighboring autonomous system within the same OAD is
          removed.
        </t>
     </section>


     <section>
       <name>AS_PATH and Path Selection</name>
       <t>
         Path selection criteria for information received from members inside
         an OAD MUST follow the same rules used for information received from
         peers inside the same autonomous system, as specified in
         <xref target="RFC4271"/>.
       </t>
       <t>
         In addition, the following rules SHALL be applied:
       </t>
       <ol>
         <li>
           If the AS_PATH is internal to the OAD, consider the neighbor AS to
           be the local AS. [???]
         </li>
         <li>
           Otherwise, consider the neighbor AS to be the leftmost AS_SEQUENCE
           AS.
         </li>
         <li>
           [Adapt for "transparent" OAD.] When comparing routes using AS_PATH
           length, CONFED_SEQUENCE and CONFED_SETs SHOULD NOT be counted.
         </li>
         <li>
           When comparing routes using the internal (IBGP learned) versus
           external (EBGP learned) rules, treat a route that is learned from a
           peer that is in the same OAD (not necessarily the same Member-AS) as
           "internal".
         </li>
       </ol>
     </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>Deployment Considerations</name>
      <t>
        Improper configuration of BGP confederations can cause routing
        information within an AS to be duplicated unnecessarily.  This
        duplication of information will waste system resources, cause
        unnecessary route flaps, and delay convergence.
      </t>
      <t>
        [LCs won't cause duplication, but they may cause inconsistencies
        if AS_PATH modifications (or use of the OAD ID) is not configured
        uniformly...the same with loop detection.]
      </t>
      <t>
        Care should be taken to manually filter duplicate advertisements
        caused by reachability information being relayed through multiple
        Member Autonomous Systems based upon the topology and redundancy
        requirements of the confederation. [Manual filtering ??]
      </t>
      <t>
        Additionally, OADs (as well as BGP confederations), by excluding
        different reachability information from consideration, have been shown
        <xref target="RFC3345"/> to cause permanent oscillation between
        candidate routes when using the tie-breaking rules required by BGP
        <xref target="RFC4271"/>.  Care must be taken when selecting MED values
        and tie-breaking policy to avoid these situations.
      </t>
      <t>
        One potential way to avoid this is by configuring inter-Member-AS IGP
        metrics higher than intra-Member-AS IGP metrics and/or using other tie-
        breaking policies to avoid BGP route selection based on incomparable
        MEDs.
      </t>
      <t>
        [Management / Configuration Text needed.]
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA. [CHECK]</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security">
        <name>Security Considerations</name>
        <t>
          This extension to BGP does not change the underlying security issues
          inherent in the existing BGP protocol, such as those described in
          <xref target="RFC4271"/> and <xref target="RFC4272"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          [Add more.]
        </t>
    </section>

    <!-- NOTE: The Acknowledgements and Contributors sections are at the end of this template -->
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>

        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.3345.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4271.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.5065.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
      </references>

      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>

        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4272.xml"/>
      </references>

    </references>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" numbered="false">
      <!-- [REPLACE/DELETE] an Acknowledgements section is optional -->
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>
        This document borrows heavily from the text in
        <xref target="RFC5065"/>.  We would like to thank the authors of that
        document as well as everyone who contributed to it.
      </t>
      <t>
        The authors would like to thank ...  for ...
      </t>
    </section>

 </back>
</rfc>
